A hundred years ago this month, a 36-year-old Albert Einstein
قبل مائة عام في مثل هذا الشهر، وقف ألبرت إينيشتاين البالغ من العمر حينها 36 عاما
stood up in front of the Prussian Academy of Sciences in Berlin
أمام أكاديمية العلوم البروسية في برلين
to present a radical new theory of space, time and gravity:
لكي يعرض نظرية ثورية تتعلق بالفضاء, الوقت والجاذبية
the general theory of relativity.
وهي النظرية العامة للنسبية.
General relativity is unquestionably Einstein's masterpiece,
تعتبر النسبية العامة وبلا شك تحفة إينشتاين الفنية،
a theory which reveals the workings of the universe at the grandest scales,
وهي النظرية التي كشفت عن طريقة عمل الكون على أعلى المقاييس،
capturing in one beautiful line of algebra
مجملة في سطر جميل لمعادلة جبرية
everything from why apples fall from trees to the beginning of time and space.
كل شئ بداية بلماذا يسقط التفاح من الأشجار وحتى بداية الخليقة والفضاء.
1915 must have been an exciting year to be a physicist.
لابد أن عام 1915 كان عاما مثيرا إذا كنت عالما فيزيائيا.
Two new ideas were turning the subject on its head.
فكرتان جديدتان تقلبان الأمر رأسا على عقب.
One was Einstein's theory of relativity,
إحداهما النظرية النسبية لإنيشتاين.
the other was arguably even more revolutionary:
أما الأخرى فلربما كانت أكثر ثورية:
quantum mechanics,
ميكانيكا الكم،
a mind-meltingly strange yet stunningly successful new way
غريبة بشكل مثير للعقل ورغم ذلك طريقة جديدة ناجحة بشكل مذهل
of understanding the microworld, the world of atoms and particles.
لفهم العالم المصغر، عالم الذرات والجسيمات.
Over the last century, these two ideas have utterly transformed
خلال القرن الماضي، بدلت هاتين الفكرتين
our understanding of the universe.
فهمنا للكون تماما.
It's thanks to relativity and quantum mechanics
فشكرا للنسبية وميكانيكا الكم
that we've learned what the universe is made from,
واللتان يرجع لهما الفضل في معرفتنا عن كيفية تكون الكون،
how it began and how it continues to evolve.
كيف بدأ وكيف يواصل رحلة التطور.
A hundred years on, we now find ourselves at another turning point in physics,
مائة عام على ذلك نجد أنفسنا الآن أمام نقطة تحول أخرى في الفيزياء،
but what's at stake now is rather different.
ولكن ماهوعلى المحك الآن مختلف تماما.
The next few years may tell us whether we'll be able
السنوات القليلة القادمة قد تخبرنا ما إذا سيكون باستطاعتنا
to continue to increase our understanding of nature,
المواصلة على تعزيز فهمنا بالطبيعة،
or whether maybe for the first time in the history of science,
أو ربما لأول مرة في تاريخ العلوم،
we could be facing questions that we cannot answer,
قد نواجه بأسئلة لن نستطيع الإجابة عليها،
not because we don't have the brains or technology,
ليس بسبب أننا نفتقد إلى العقول والتقنية،
but because the laws of physics themselves forbid it.
ولكن بسبب أن قوانين الفيزياء نفسها تمنع ذلك.
This is the essential problem: the universe is far, far too interesting.
هذه هي المشكلة الأساسية، مازال العالم مثيرا للإهتمام بشكل كبير.
Relativity and quantum mechanics appear to suggest
تقترح النسبية وميكانيكا الكم
that the universe should be a boring place.
أن الكون يجب أن يكون مكانا مملاً.
It should be dark, lethal and lifeless.
لابد أن يكون مظلماً ومشوه خلقياً ويفتقر إلى الحياة.
But when we look around us, we see we live in a universe full of interesting stuff,
ولكن عندما ننظر حولنا نجد أننا نعيش في كون ملئ بالأشياء المثيرة،
full of stars, planets, trees, squirrels.
ملئ بالنجوم، والكواكب، والأشجار، والسناجب.
The question is, ultimately,
والسؤال هو، في نهاية المطاف،
why does all this interesting stuff exist?
لماذا توجد كل هذه الأشياء المثيرة؟
Why is there something rather than nothing?
لماذا يوجد شئ بدلا عن لا شئ؟
This contradiction is the most pressing problem in fundamental physics,
هذا التناقض هو المشكلة الأكثر إلحاحا في الفيزياء الأساسية،
and in the next few years, we may find out whether we'll ever be able to solve it.
وخلال السنين القليلة القادمة، قد نعرف ما إذا سيكون باستطاعتنا حلها.
At the heart of this problem are two numbers,
في قلب هذه المشكلة يوجد رقمان،
two extremely dangerous numbers.
رقمان شديدا الخطورة للغاية.
These are properties of the universe that we can measure,
يمثلان خصائص الكون والتي بمقدورنا قياسها،
and they're extremely dangerous
وهما خطيران للغاية
because if they were different, even by a tiny bit,
بسبب أنه إذا طرأ عليهما إختلاف، ولو حتى قليلا،
then the universe as we know it would not exist.
فإن الكون الذي نعرفه قد لا يوجد.
The first of these numbers is associated with the discovery that was made
الرقم الأول مرتبط بالإكتشاف الذي تم
a few kilometers from this hall, at CERN, home of this machine,
على بعد بضعة كيلومترات من هذه القاعة، في مختبر سيرن، مقر هذه الآلة،
the largest scientific device ever built by the human race,
أضخم جهاز علمي تم بناؤه على الإطلاق من قبل بني الإنسان،
the Large Hadron Collider.
مصادم الهادرون الضخم.
The LHC whizzes subatomic particles around a 27-kilometer ring,
ينطلق مصادم الهادرون الضخم بالجسيمات دون الذرية حول حلقة تبلغ 27 كيلومترا،
getting them closer and closer to the speed of light
مما يجعلها أقرب إلى سرعة الضوء
before smashing them into each other inside gigantic particle detectors.
قبل أن يصادمها بعضها البعض داخل أجهزة عملاقة للكشف عن الجسيمات.
On July 4, 2012, physicists at CERN announced to the world
في 4 يونيو 2012، أعلن فيزيائيون في سيرن للعالم
that they'd spotted a new fundamental particle
أنهم رصدوا جسيما أساسيا جديدا
being created at the violent collisions at the LHC: the Higgs boson.
تم الحصول عليه في الإصطدامات العنيفة داخل مصادم الهادرون الضخم: هيغز بوزون.
Now, if you followed the news at the time,
الآن، إذا ما تابعتم الأخبار في تلك الفترة،
you'll have seen a lot of physicists getting very excited indeed,
لكنتم رأيتم العديد من الفيريائيين متحمسين جدا في الواقع،
and you'd be forgiven for thinking
ويمكن المغفرة لكم إن كنتم تفكرون
we get that way every time we discover a new particle.
أنه يحدث ذلك في كل مرة نكتشف فيها جسيما جديدا.
Well, that is kind of true,
حسنا، يحمل ذلك شيئا من الحقيقة،
but the Higgs boson is particularly special.
ولكن الهيغز بوزون خاص للغاية.
We all got so excited because finding the Higgs
جميعنا أصيب بالإثارة بسبب اكتشافنا للهيغز
proves the existence of a cosmic energy field.
مما يثبت وجود حقل طاقة كونية.
Now, you may have trouble imagining an energy field,
الآن، قد تواجهون بعض المصاعب في تخيل حقل الطاقة،
but we've all experienced one.
لكم قد حدث ذلك لنا جميعا.
If you've ever held a magnet close to a piece of metal
إذا ما قربت مغناطيسا لقطعة حديد
and felt a force pulling across that gap,
وشعرت بقوة سحب عبر ذلك الفراغ،
then you've felt the effect of a field.
إذاً فقد شعرت بتأثير الحقل.
And the Higgs field is a little bit like a magnetic field,
وحقل الهيغز هو بعض الشئ مثل حقل مغناطيسي،
except it has a constant value everywhere.
بخلاف أنه يحوي قيمة ثابتة في كل مكان.
It's all around us right now.
إنه في كل مكان حولنا الآن.
We can't see it or touch it,
لا نستطيع رؤيته أو لمسه،
but if it wasn't there,
ولكن إن لم يكن هنالك،
we would not exist.
ما كان لنا أن نوجد.
The Higgs field gives mass
يعطي حقل الهيغز الكتلة
to the fundamental particles that we're made from.
للجسيمات الأساسية والتي نتكون منها.
If it wasn't there, those particles would have no mass,
إن لم يكن موجودا، فسوف لن تحتوي تلك الجسيمات على كتلة،
and no atoms could form and there would be no us.
ولن تتكوّن الذرات وهكذا لن نوجد نحن.
But there is something deeply mysterious about the Higgs field.
ولكن هناك شيئ غامض جدا يتعلق بحقل الهيغز.
Relativity and quantum mechanics tell us that it has two natural settings,
تخبرنا النسبية وميكانيكا الكم أنه يحتوي على وضعين طبيعيين للضبط،
a bit like a light switch.
يشبه مفتاح الضوء.
It should either be off,
إما أن يكون في وضع الإغلاق،
so that it has a zero value everywhere in space,
في هذه الحالة يحتوي على قيمة صفرية في كل مكان في الفضاء،
or it should be on so it has an absolutely enormous value.
أو أن يكون في وضع العمل وفي هذه الحالة يحتوي على قيم متعددة.
In both of these scenarios, atoms could not exist,
في كلا من هذين التصورين فإن الذرات لا وجود لها،
and therefore all the other interesting stuff
وبالتالي كل الأِشياء المثيرة الأخرى
that we see around us in the universe would not exist.
التي نراها حولنا سوف لن توجد.
In reality, the Higgs field is just slightly on,
في الواقع فإن حقل هيغز في حالة عمل بشكل طفيف،
not zero but 10,000 trillion times weaker than its fully on value,
ليس صفرا ولكن 10000 تريليون مرة أضعف مما قد يكون عليه في حالة العمل،
a bit like a light switch that's got stuck just before the off position.
أشبه بمفتاح المصباح الذي علق قبل وضع الإقفال.
And this value is crucial.
وهذه القيمة حرجة.
If it were a tiny bit different,
فإذا ما كانت مختلفة ولو قليلاً،
then there would be no physical structure in the universe.
فسوف لن يكون هناك أي بنية مادية للكون.
So this is the first of our dangerous numbers,
لذلك، هذه أول أرقامنا الخطرة،
the strength of the Higgs field.
قوة مجال هيغز.
Theorists have spent decades trying to understand
قضى المنظرون عقوداً وهم يحاولون فهم
why it has this very peculiarly fine-tuned number,
لماذا لها هذا الرقم المحكم بشكل غريب،
and they've come up with a number of possible explanations.
ثم توصلوا إلى عدد من التفسيرات المحتملة.
They have sexy-sounding names like "supersymmetry"
تتمتع بأسماء مثيرة مثل "التناظر الفائق"
or "large extra dimensions."
أو "الأبعاد الإضافية الكبرى."
I'm not going to go into the details of these ideas now,
لن أتناول تفاصيل هذه الأفكار حاليا،
but the key point is this:
ولكن النقطة الأساسية هي هذه:
if any of them explained this weirdly fine-tuned value of the Higgs field,
إذا ما فسرت إحداها هذه القيمة المحكمة بشكل غريب لحقل هيغز،
then we should see new particles being created at the LHC
إذاً لابد أن نرى جسيمات جديدة يتم خلقها في مصادم الهادرون الضخم
along with the Higgs boson.
جنبا إلى جنب مع هيغز بوزون.
So far, though, we've not seen any sign of them.
حتى الآن، لم نرى أي إشارة على ذلك.
But there's actually an even worse example
ولكن في الواقع يوجد مثال أسوء حتى
of this kind of fine-tuning of a dangerous number,
من هذا النوع المحكم لهذا الرقم الخطر،
and this time it comes from the other end of the scale,
وتأتي هذه المرة من الطرف الآخر من المقياس،
from studying the universe at vast distances.
من واقع دراسة الكون في مسافات شاسعة.
One of the most important consequences of Einstein's general theory of relativity
واحدة من أهم نتائج نظرية إينشتاين العامة للنسبية
was the discovery that the universe began as a rapid expansion of space and time
كان اكتشاف أن العالم بدأ نتيجة تمدد مفاجئ للفضاء والوقت
13.8 billion years ago, the Big Bang.
منذ 13.8 مليار سنة خلت والمسمى بالإنفجار العظيم.
Now, according to early versions of the Big Bang theory,
الآن، طبقا للنسخ الأولى من نظرية الإنفجار العظيم،
the universe has been expanding ever since
كان الكون يتمدد منذ ذلك الوقت
with gravity gradually putting the brakes on that expansion.
مع وجود الجاذبية التي كانت تعرقل ذلك التمدد بشكل تدريجي.
But in 1998, astronomers made the stunning discovery
ولكن في عام 1998 توصل علماء الفلك إلى الاكتشاف المذهل
that the expansion of the universe is actually speeding up.
أن تمدد الكون في الواقع آخذ في التسارع.
The universe is getting bigger and bigger faster and faster
الكون يتمدد ويتمدد وبشكل أسرع وأسرع
driven by a mysterious repulsive force called dark energy.
مدفوعا بقوة غامضة طاردة تدعى الطاقة المظلمة.
Now, whenever you hear the word "dark" in physics,
الآن، متى ما سمعت كلمة "مظلم" في الفيزياء،
you should get very suspicious
لابد أن يعتريك الشك
because it probably means we don't know what we're talking about.
بسبب أنها قد تعني أننا لا نعرف ما نتحدث عنه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We don't know what dark energy is,
نحن لا نعرف ما تعنيه الطاقة المظلمة،
but the best idea is that it's the energy of empty space itself,
ولكن التفسير الأفضل أنها طاقة الفضاء الفارغ نفسه،
the energy of the vacuum.
طاقة الفراغ.
Now, if you use good old quantum mechanics to work out
الآن، إذا ما استخدمت ميكانيكا الكم القديمة
how strong dark energy should be,
كم يجب أن تكون قوة الطاقة المظلمة،
you get an absolutely astonishing result.
ستتحصل على نتيجة مذهلة بكل معنى الكلمة.
You find that dark energy
ستجد أن الطاقة المظلمة
should be 10 to the power of 120 times stronger
لابد أن تمثل 10 من الطاقة إلى 120 مرة أقوى
than the value we observe from astronomy.
من القيمة التي نرقبها من علم الفلك.
That's one with 120 zeroes after it.
هذا الرقم يتكون من واحد متبوعا ب 120 صفرا.
This is a number so mind-bogglingly huge
هذا رقم ضخم للغاية
that it's impossible to get your head around.
الشئ الذي يجعل من المستحيل الإحاطة به.
We often use the word "astronomical" when we're talking about big numbers.
غالبا ما نستخدم كلمة "فلكي" حينما يتعلق الأمر بأرقام ضخمة.
Well, even that one won't do here.
ولكن حتى ذلك لا يجدي هنا.
This number is bigger than any number in astronomy.
هذا الرقم أضخم من أي رقم آخر في علم الفلك.
It's a thousand trillion trillion trillion times bigger
إنه أضخم بترليون ترليون ترليون مرة
than the number of atoms in the entire universe.
من رقم الذرات في كل الكون.
So that's a pretty bad prediction.
لذلك فإنه تنبؤ سيء جدا.
In fact, it's been called the worst prediction in physics,
في الحقيقة، وصف ذلك بأنه أسوء تنبؤ في الفيزياء،
and this is more than just a theoretical curiosity.
وهذا أكثر من مجرد فضول نظري.
If dark energy were anywhere near this strong,
إذا ما كانت الطاقة المظلمة في كل مكان بهذه القوة،
then the universe would have been torn apart,
إذا لتمزق الكون إربا إربا،
stars and galaxies could not form, and we would not be here.
ما كانت النجوم والمجرات لتتكون، وما كنا لنوجد نحن.
So this is the second of those dangerous numbers,
إذاً هذا هو ثاني الأرقام الخطرة،
the strength of dark energy,
قوة الطاقة المظلمة،
and explaining it requires an even more fantastic level of fine-tuning
وتفسيرها يتطلب مستوى أكثر روعة من الصقل
than we saw for the Higgs field.
أكثر من ما نرى في حقل هيغز.
But unlike the Higgs field, this number has no known explanation.
وعلى عكس حقل هيغز، ليس لهذا الرقم تفسير معروف.
The hope was that a complete combination
كان الأمل هو دمج كامل
of Einstein's general theory of relativity,
لنظرية إينشتاين العامة للنسبية،
which is the theory of the universe at grand scales,
وهي نظرية الكون على نطاقات واسعة،
with quantum mechanics, the theory of the universe at small scales,
مع ميكانيكا الكم، وهي نظرية الكون على نطاقات صغيرة،
might provide a solution.
قد تقدم حلاً.
Einstein himself spent most of his later years
قضى إينشتاين معظم سنينه الأخيرة
on a futile search for a unified theory of physics,
في بحث لا طائل منه من أجل نظرية موحدة للفيزياء،
and physicists have kept at it ever since.
وقد سار الفيزيائييون على نهجه منذ ذلك الوقت.
One of the most promising candidates for a unified theory is string theory,
أحد المرشحين الواعدين لنظرية موحدة هي نظرية الأوتار،
and the essential idea is,
والفكرة الأساسية هي،
if you could zoom in on the fundamental particles that make up our world,
إذا ما كان بإستطاعتك أن تكبر الجسيمات الأساسية والتي تكون عالمنا،
you'd see actually that they're not particles at all,
في الواقع سترى أنها ليست جسيمات على الإطلاق،
but tiny vibrating strings of energy,
بل سلاسل مهتزة صغيرة من الطاقة،
with each frequency of vibration corresponding to a different particle,
مع كل تردد من الذبذبة يتوافق مع جزييء آخر،
a bit like musical notes on a guitar string.
مثل حروف موسيقية على أوتار الغيتار.
So it's a rather elegant, almost poetic way of looking at the world,
حتى أنها طريقة أنيقة وبالأحرى شاعرية في النظر إلى العالم،
but it has one catastrophic problem.
ولكن هناك مشكلة كارثية واحدة.
It turns out that string theory isn't one theory at all,
إتضح أن نظرية الأوتار ليست نظرية واحدة فقط،
but a whole collection of theories.
بل مجموعة من النظريات.
It's been estimated, in fact,
في الواقع، تم تقدير
that there are 10 to the 500 different versions of string theory.
أن هناك من 10 إلى 500 نسخة مختلفة من نظرية الأوتار.
Each one would describe a different universe
كل واحدة منها قد تصف كونا مختلفا
with different laws of physics.
بالإستعانة بقوانين فيزياء مختلفة.
Now, critics say this makes string theory unscientific.
الآن، يقول النقاد أن هذا يجعل من نظرية الأوتار نظرية غير علمية.
You can't disprove the theory.
لا يمكنك دحض النظرية.
But others actually turned this on its head
ولكن الآخرين قلبوا الأمر رأسا على عقب
and said, well, maybe this apparent failure
فقالوا، ربما هذا الفشل الواضح
is string theory's greatest triumph.
هو أعظم نجاح لنظرية الأوتار.
What if all of these 10 to the 500 different possible universes
ماذا لو كانت هذه ال10 إلى 500 كون مختلف محتملة
actually exist out there somewhere
موجودة في مكان ما هناك
in some grand multiverse?
في كون متعدد ضخم ما؟
Suddenly we can understand
سنفهم فجأة
the weirdly fine-tuned values of these two dangerous numbers.
القيم المحكمة بشكل غريب لهذين الرقمين الخطرين.
In most of the multiverse,
في غالب الكون المتعدد
dark energy is so strong that the universe gets torn apart,
تكون الطاقة المظلمة قوية جدا مما يسبب تمزق الكون إربا إربا،
or the Higgs field is so weak that no atoms can form.
أو أن يكون مجال هيغز ضعيفا جدا مما لا يسمح بتكوين أي ذرات.
We live in one of the places in the multiverse
نحن نعيش في أحد أماكن الكون المتعدد
where the two numbers are just right.
حيث أن كلا الرقمين صحيح تماما.
We live in a Goldilocks universe.
نحن نعيش في عالم معتدل.
Now, this idea is extremely controversial, and it's easy to see why.
الآن، هذه الفكرة موضع خلاف وبشدة، ومن السهل علينا معرفة السبب.
If we follow this line of thinking,
لو إتبعنا طريقة التفكير هذه،
then we will never be able to answer the question,
حينها لن يكون بإمكاننا الإجابة على السؤال،
"Why is there something rather than nothing?"
"لماذا هناك شئ بدلا عن لا شئ؟"
In most of the multiverse, there is nothing,
في غالب الكون المتعدد لا يوجد شئ،
and we live in one of the few places
ونحن نعيش في واحد من الأماكن القليلة
where the laws of physics allow there to be something.
حيث تسمح قوانين الفيزياء بوجود شئ ما.
Even worse, we can't test the idea of the multiverse.
الأمر أسوء من ذلك، إذ ليس بمقدورنا إختبار فكرة الكون المتعدد.
We can't access these other universes,
ليس باستطاعتنا الوصول إلى هذه الأكوان الأخرى،
so there's no way of knowing whether they're there or not.
بالتالي ليس هناك من طريقة لنعرف ما إذا كانت موجودة أم لا.
So we're in an extremely frustrating position.
لذلك نحن في موقف محبط للغاية.
That doesn't mean the multiverse doesn't exist.
ذلك لا يعني أن الكون المتعدد لا وجود له.
There are other planets, other stars, other galaxies,
هناك كواكب أخرى ونجوم أخرى ومجرات أخرى،
so why not other universes?
فلماذا لا تكون هناك أكوان أخرى؟
The problem is, it's unlikely we'll ever know for sure.
المشكلة هي، أنه من غير المحتمل أننا سنتأكد من ذلك.
Now, the idea of the multiverse has been around for a while,
الآن، فكرة الكون المتعدد موجودة منذ مدة،
but in the last few years, we've started to get the first solid hints
ولكن خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية، بدأنا نحصل على أولى التلميحات المؤكدة
that this line of reasoning may get born out.
أن هذا الخط من التفكير قد يبصر النور.
Despite high hopes for the first run of the LHC,
على الرغم من الآمال الكبيرة عند أول تشغيل لمصادم الهادرون الضخم،
what we were looking for there --
عن ماذا كنا نبحث هناك --
we were looking for new theories of physics:
كنا نبحث عن نظريات فيزياء جديدة:
supersymmetry or large extra dimensions
التناظر الفائق أو الأبعاد الإضافية الكبرى
that could explain this weirdly fine-tuned value of the Higgs field.
تلك قد تفسر هذه القيمة المحكمة بشكل غريب لمجال هيغز.
But despite high hopes, the LHC revealed a barren subatomic wilderness
لكن رغم الآمال الكبيرة كشف مصادم الهادرون الضخم عن مقدار ضخم من الجسيمات دون الذرية
populated only by a lonely Higgs boson.
مأهولة بمجال هيغز وحيد.
My experiment published paper after paper
تم نشر تجربتي ورقة ورقة
where we glumly had to conclude that we saw no signs of new physics.
حيث توجب علينا الإنتهاء بأسف إلى أننا لم نرى أي إشارات على وجود فيزياء جديدة.
The stakes now could not be higher.
الرهان الآن لا يمكن أن يكون أعلى من ذلك.
This summer, the LHC began its second phase of operation
في هذا الصيف، بدأ مصادم الهادرون الضخم المرحلة الثانية من عمله
with an energy almost double what we achieved in the first run.
بطاقة تعادل تقريبا ضعف تلك التي أنجزناها في الجولة الأولى.
What particle physicists are all desperately hoping for
ما يأمل فيه فيزيائيو الجسيمات وبشدة
are signs of new particles, micro black holes,
هو رصد إشارات على وجود جسيمات جديدة أو ثقوب سوداء صغيرة
or maybe something totally unexpected
أو ربما شئ غير متوقع بالمرة
emerging from the violent collisions at the Large Hadron Collider.
ينبثق من الإصطدامات العنيفة داخل مصادم الهادرون الضخم.
If so, then we can continue this long journey
لو حدث ذلك، حينها سيمكننا مواصلة هذه الرحلة الطويلة
that began 100 years ago with Albert Einstein
والتي بدأت منذ 100 عام مضت بألبرت إينشتاين
towards an ever deeper understanding of the laws of nature.
حتى فهم أعمق لقوانين الطبيعة.
But if, in two or three years' time,
ولكن لو، خلال فترة زمنية من سنتين أو ثلاث
when the LHC switches off again for a second long shutdown,
عندما يتم إغلاق مصادم الهادرون الضخم لإغلاق طويل ثاني،
we've found nothing but the Higgs boson,
لم نجد شيئا غير هيغز بوزون،
then we may be entering a new era in physics:
حينها قد ندخل مرحلة جديدة من الفيزياء:
an era where there are weird features of the universe that we cannot explain;
حيث توجد ملامح غريبة للكون لا يكون باستطاعتنا تفسيرها:
an era where we have hints that we live in a multiverse
وحيث تتوافر لنا تلميحات أننا نعيش في كون متعدد
that lies frustratingly forever beyond our reach;
والذي يقع وبشكل محبط بعيدا عن متناولنا وإلى الأبد
an era where we will never be able to answer the question,
في عصر لن نتمكن فيه من الإجابة على السؤال التالي،
"Why is there something rather than nothing?"
"لماذا يوجد شئ بدلا عن لا شئ؟"
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Harry, even if you just said
برونو غيواساني: هاري، حتى وإن قلت
the science may not have some answers,
أن العلم قد لا يملك بعض الإجابات،
I would like to ask you a couple of questions, and the first is:
أريد أن أطرح عليك بعض الأسئلة، وأولها هو:
building something like the LHC is a generational project.
بناء شئ مثل مصادم الهادرون الضخم يعتبر مشروع الأجيال.
I just mentioned, introducing you, that we live in a short-term world.
ذكرت في معرض تقديمي لك، أننا نعيش في عالم قصير المدى.
How do you think so long term,
كيف ترى المدى الطويل لذلك،
projecting yourself out a generation when building something like this?
عند إسقاط نفسك خارج جيل عند بناء شئ كهذا؟
Harry Cliff: I was very lucky
هاري كليف: لقد كنت محظوظا للغاية
that I joined the experiment I work on at the LHC in 2008,
عندما إلتحقت بتجربة العمل في مصادم الهادرون الضخم في عام 2008،
just as we were switching on,
تماما كما كنا نبدأ العمل،
and there are people in my research group who have been working on it
وهناك أناس في فريقي البحثي كانوا يعملون عليه
for three decades, their entire careers on one machine.
لمدة ثلاث عقود، قضوا جل فتراتهم المهنية على آلة واحدة.
So I think the first conversations about the LHC were in 1976,
لذلك أغتقد أن أولى الحوارات حول مصادم الهادرون الضخم دارت عام 1976،
and you start planning the machine without the technology
وبدأ التخطيط لهذه الآلة في غياب التكنولوجيا
that you know you're going to need to be able to build it.
التي تعلم أنك ستحتاج لها حتى تتمكن من بناء هذا الشئ.
So the computing power did not exist in the early '90s
بالتالي فإن القدرة الحاسوبية لم تكن موجودة في بداية التسعينيات
when design work began in earnest.
عندما بدأت أعمال التصميم بشكل جدي.
One of the big detectors which record these collisions,
أحد أجهزة الكشف التي تسجل هذه التصادمات،
they didn't think there was technology
لم يظنوا أن هناك تقنية
that could withstand the radiation that would be created in the LHC,
يمكن أن تصمد أمام الإشعاع الذي ينشأ في مصادم الهادرون الضخم،
so there was basically a lump of lead in the middle of this object
كان هناك قطعة من الرصاص في منتصف هذا الشئ
with some detectors around the outside,
مع بعض الكواشف في الخارج،
but subsequently we have developed technology.
ولكن من ثم طورنا تقنية.
So you have to rely on people's ingenuity, that they will solve the problems,
لذلك عليك الإعتماد على إبداع الناس كونهم سيحلون المشاكل،
BG: China just announced two or three weeks ago
برونو: أعلنت الصين قبل أسبوعين أو ثلاثة أسابيع
that they intend to build
أنها تنوي بناء
a supercollider twice the size of the LHC.
مصادم خارق يعادل ضعفي حجم مصادم الهادرون الضخم.
I was wondering how you and your colleagues welcome the news.
كنت أتساءل كيف استقبلت أنت وزملاؤك هذه الأخبار.
HC: Size isn't everything, Bruno. BG: I'm sure. I'm sure.
هاري: ليس الحجم هو كل شئ يا برونو. برونو: أنا متأكد. أنا متأكد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It sounds funny for a particle physicist to say that.
يبدو ذلك طريفا أن يقول فيزيائي جسيمات شيئا من هذا القبيل.
But I mean, seriously, it's great news.
ولكن أعني، بشكل جدي أنها أخبار عظيمة.
So building a machine like the LHC
بالتالي فإن بناء ماكينة مثل مصادم الهادرون الضخم
requires countries from all over the world to pool their resources.
يتطلب بلدانا من جميع أنحاء العالم لتساهم بمواردها.
No one nation can afford to build a machine this large,
لا تستطيع أمة واحدة تحمل بناء ماكينة بهذه الضخامة
apart from maybe China,
ربما ما عدا الصين،
because they can mobilize huge amounts of resources,
لأن بمقدورهم تعبئة كميات ضخمة من الموارد،
manpower and money to build machines like this.
مثل الطاقات البشرية والمال لبناء ماكينات كهذه.
So it's only a good thing.
لذلك فهي أخبار جيدة.
What they're really planning to do is to build a machine
ما يخططون لفعله حقا هو بناء ماكينة
that will study the Higgs boson in detail and could give us some clues
سيكون بمقدورها دراسة البوزون هيغز بالتفصيل وإمدادنا ببعض الأدلة
as to whether these new ideas, like supersymmetry, are really out there,
ما إذا كانت هذه الأفكار الجديدة من شاكلة التناظر الفائق موجودة حقا،
so it's great news for physics, I think.
في المجمل أعتقد أنها أخبار عظيمة للفيزياء.
BG: Harry, thank you. HC: Thank you very much.
برونو: هاري، شكرا لك. هاري: شكرا جزيلا لك.
(Applause)
(تصيق)